Finding Aid for Department of Romance Languages and Literatures (University of Michigan) Records 1907-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Romance Languages and Literatures (University of Michigan) records
1907-2003
1920-1998
University of Michigan. Department of Romance Languages.
Records of the University of Michigan Department of Romance Languages and Literatures. The collection contains administrative and topical files of the Department, records of associated student organizations, photographs, and audio material. Of particular note is the extensive run of photographs (1908-1955) of photographs of the Cercle Français' annual French-language play.
0048 Bimu 2
4.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records of the Department of Romance Languages and Literatures were received in 1999. Donor no. 8871.
The records are open for research.
The first modern language taught at the University of Michigan was French, offered in 1847 by Louis Fasquelle. Spanish, Italian, Portuguese and German were added sporadically over the next four decades, taught by Fasquelle and other appointed instructors. In 1887 the Regents granted a petition for the official and separate formations of the Department of Romance Languages and Literatures and the Department of Germanic Languages and Literatures. Special courses in French, Spanish and German for engineering students were created in 1889. From 1904 until 1928 these courses were taught by a professor of modern languages within Engineering. In 1928, however, this responsibility was transferred back to each respective department in the College of Literature, Science and the Arts. The Department of Romance Languages and Literatures has continued to offer instruction in the languages, literatures, and civilizations of France, Spain, Latin America, Italy, and Portugal, with occasional courses in such fields as Rumanian, Catalan, and Francophone areas outside of France. Graduate courses have been offered since 1858, when the first advanced coursework in French was offered. In 1949 a program in Romance Linguistics was added to the department, including undergraduate coursework and a separate graduate degree program. This program is not currently offered.
The department has additionally been involved in several programs over the years. With the beginning of World War II, special language training courses were developed in all sections of the department for students soon to enter into military service. These courses continued until 1945. In the summer of 1942, staff from the department provided language and area studies for the Civil Affairs Specialist Training Program and language training for the Army Specialist Training Program. A special program was also set up during postwar years for the training of field officers for various postwar assignments in Latin America. In the summer of 1956 the department took an active part in the national Foreign Language in the Elementary School program, establishing training programs for elementary school teachers in the instruction of French and Spanish. In the summer of 1959 the department ran an institute supported by the National Defense Education Act offering special remedial training to high school language teachers and superintendents.
Extracurricular student activities have been active at different points in the department's history. The Cercle Français was organized in 1902 by and for students of French. This organization was particularly active from the 1930s through the 1950s, supported by both the University and City of Ann Arbor communities and producing an annual play and an annual French lecture series. Spanish organizations such as Sigma Delta Pi, the national Spanish honor society, and the Sociedad Hispanica, were active as well during this time.
Today the Department of Romance Languages and Literatures offers courses in French, Italian, Portuguese, Spanish, and Romance Linguistics, focusing on language, literature, and culture. For current information about the department, see the department web site, located at the following URL: http://www.lsa.umich.edu/rll.
For more detailed information on the history of the department, particularly the early years, see the University of Michigan Encyclopedic Survey, and the folder entitled "Department History" located in Box 2 of this record group.
The records of the Department of 77Romance Language provide some documentation of the administration of the department and several student organizations including Sigma Delta Pi, the Sociedad Hispanica and the Cercle Français. This record group is divided into five series: Department Administration, Faculty Information, Student Organizations, Topical, and Audio-Visual.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Department of Romance Languages.; Language and languages--Study and teaching.; Language and education.; Romance languages--Study and teaching.; Romance literature--Study and teaching.; University of Michigan. Cercle Français.; Sigma Delta Pi.; Sociedad Hispanica (University of Michigan); Spanish language--Societies, etc.; French language--Societies, etc.
Subjects - Visual Material:
University of Michigan. Department of Romance Languages.; French language--Societies, etc.; Spanish language--Societies, etc.; University of Michigan. Cercle Français.; Sociedad Hispanica (University of Michigan); Sigma Delta Pi.; Photographs.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Department Administration
  Department Administration is the largest series in this record group, spanning 1 linear foot, and contains materials from the years 1926 to 1986, with sporadic concentrations of material from across those years in different areas. Subseries within this series include budget and salary information from the years 1970-1986, committee records and correspondence, including a substantial run of Executive Committee minutes and materials from 1933 to 1944; course administration materials, including enrollment and courseload statistics from 1947 to 1983; department reports, including the "Report on Department Activities" 1926 to 1927 and 1928 to 1931; graduate program information; and position requests, 1984-1986.
  - Budget and Salaries (Box 1)
    - 1970-1980 (Box 1)
    - 1981-1986 (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Committee on Curricular Flexibility, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Foreign Language Instruction, 1953-1959 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Higher Education, 1961 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee Minutes and Materials
      - 1933-1936 (Box 1)
      - 1936-1938 (Box 1)
      - 1938-1942 (Box 1)
      - 1942-1944 (Box 1)
      - Subcommittee on Language Instruction, 1944 (Box 1)
    - French Section, 1983-1987 (Box 1)
    - Humanities Group, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Senior Advisory and Executive Committee Meetings, 1954-1958 (Box 1)
    - Senior Spanish Staff Meetings, 1948-1963 (Box 1)
    - Teacher Education Committee, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Course Administration
    - Course Approvals, 1938-1973 (Box 1)
    - Course Placement
      - Advanced Placement Credit, 1982-1986 (Box 1)
      - CEEB Testing, 1964-1965 (Box 1)
      - Changes in Course Election, 1960; 1970 (Box 1)
    - Elementary Spanish, 1966-1974; undated (Box 1)
    - History-French Subject, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Language Requirement, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Preliminary Exam Questions, 1949-1959 (Box 1)
    - Statistics
      - 1947-1958 (Box 1)
      - 1977-1978 (Box 1)
      - 1982-1983 (Box 1)
    - Summer Session Administration
      - 1915-1938 (Box 1)
      - 1960 (Box 1)
      - 1963 (Box 1)
      - 1964 (Box 1)
      - 1965 (Box 1)
      - 1967-1968 (Box 1)
      - 1969 (Box 1)
    - Teaching Assistant Assignments, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Department Reports
    - Report on Department Activities, 1926-1927 (Box 1)
    - Report on Department Activities, 1928-1931 (Box 1)
    - Report on Present and Future Staff Arrangements, 1952 (Box 1)
    - State of the Department, 1958; 1960; 1964 (Box 1)
  - Graduate Program Description and Statistics, 1975-1985 (Box 1)
  - Position Requests
    - 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - 1986 (Box 1)
  - Teaching Loads, 1956-60, 1943-1944; 1945; 1974 (Box 1)
- Faculty Information
  Faculty Information spans the years from 1941 to 1981. This series includes bibliographies of publications by faculty members from 1852 to 1965, evaluations by students and by the professors themselves, information on faculty members holding foreign degrees and faculty members who know Russian, faculty personnel records 1941-1942, and promotion requests, 1942-1952.
  - Bibliography (Box 2)
    - 1852-1937 (Box 2)
    - 1852-1951 (Box 2)
    - 1945-1947 (Box 2)
    - 1954-1965 (Box 2)
  - Evaluations
    - By Students, 1950-1964 (Box 2)
    - By Faculty, 1941-1942 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Members Holding Foreign Degrees, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Members Who Know Russian (Box 2)
  - Faculty Personnel Records, 1941-1942
    - Assistant and Associate Professors (Box 2)
    - Professors (Box 2)
  - Promotion Requests
    - 1942-1952 (Box 2)
    - Tenure Review of Raymonde Carroll, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - Tenure Review of Walter Mignolo, 1980-1981 (Box 2)
- Student Organizations
  Student Organizations spans the years 1924 to 1965, and includes materials from two organizations. The Sigma Delta Pi subseries includes membership information, accounts and correspondence between 1948 and 1964. A file of photographs from this organization has been removed to the Audio-visual series. The Sociedad Hispanica subseries includes records, correspondence, and miscellany including play programs and tickets to lecture series, spanning 1924 to 1965. Photographs from this subseries have also been removed to the Audio-visual series. Cercle Franççais, a French language organization, is represented in the Audio-Visual series.
  - Cercle Français
    - 1940-1971 (Box 2)
    - Ledger/Journal, 1930-1942 (Box 2)
    - Lecture Programs, 1914-1945 (Box 2)
    - Play (Représentation) Programs, 1914-1925 (Box 2)
    - Play (Représentation) Programs. undated., 1926-1961 (Box 2)
    - Soirée Programs, 1913-1931 (Box 2)
  - Sigma Delta Pi
    - Members, 1949-1958 (Box 2)
    - Accounts and Correspondence, 1948-1964; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Sociedad Hispanica
    - Records and Correspondence
      - 1937-1954 (Box 2)
      - 1954-1955 (Box 2)
      - 1955-1961 (Box 2)
      - 1961-1965 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Lecture Series Tickets, 1926-1927; 1942-1943 (Box 2)
      - Play Programs, 1924; 1926; 1927 (Box 2)
- Topical
  The Topical series includes materials on various topics of departmental concern from 1928 to 1975. Notable within this series are a Departmental History file including a letter confirming the consolidation of the Department in 1928, and an extensive run of correspondence documenting University Lectures related to the department from 1956 to 1975. Also within this series are programs and correspondence from 1963-1987 (including such notable people as Barbara Jordan, Beverly Sills, Alice Walker, Toni Morrison, and Emmanuel Le Roy Ladurie) related to the Hayward Keniston Lectures.
  - Charles F. Fraker Conference, 1992-1998 (Box 2)
  - Departmental History, 1928; 1944 (Box 2)
  - Faculty Complaints about Department, 1933 (Box 2)
  - GEO Grievance, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Hayward Keniston Lectures
    - Flyers and Programs, 1975-1996 (Box 2)
    - Lectures Correspondence, 1973-1987 (Box 2)
  - Jean Cardiner Memorial Lecture, 1991 (Box 2)
  - Maison Française, 1938-1974 (Box 3)
  - Nanterre Lecturer Exchange, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Study Abroad
    - Junior Year in Barcelona, 1970 (Box 3)
    - Junior Year in France, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Junior Year in Spain, 1963-1970 (Box 3)
    - Summer Study Programs in France and Spain, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Tardiness to Class in Frieze Building, 1958 (Box 3)
  - Teaching of Foreign Languages in Elementary Schools, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Training of College Teachers, 1948 (Box 3)
  - Tutorial Sections for Veterans, 1946 (Box 3)
  - University Lectures Correspondence
    - 1956-1961 (Box 3)
    - 1961-1965 (Box 3)
    - 1965-1972 (Box 3)
    - 1972-1975 (Box 3)
- Audio-Visual
  Audio-Visual includes sound recordings and photographs. Photographs span the years from 1908 to 1964, and document student organizations and some staff and faculty. Notable is a run of pictures of the Cercle Français plays, 1908-1956. Audio materials include a record on Spanish pronunciation, and magnetic tape reels in French used in 1968.
  The Audio-Visual series includes sound recordings and photographs. Photographs span the years from 1914 to 1964, and document student organizations. Notable is a run of pictures of the Cercle Français plays, 1914-1956. Audio materials include a record on Spanish pronunciation, and magnetic tape reels in French used in 1968.
  - Photographs
    - Cercle Français Members
      - 1924-1925 (Box 3)
      - 1925-1926 (Box 3)
    - Cercle Français Plays
      - "L'Avare", 1908 (Box 3)
      - "Le Barbier de Séville", 1909 (Box 3)
      - "Le malade imaginaire", 1910 (Box 3)
      - "Les Romanesques" / "Les Précieuses Ridicules", 1911 (Box 3)
      - "Le Monde où l'on s'ennuie", 1912 (Box 4)
      - "Le Fourberies de Scapin", 1913 (Box 4)
      - "L'Assaut", 1914 (Box 3)
      - "La Poudre aux yeux", 1915 (Box 3)
      - "Les Pattes de Mouche", 1917 (Box 4)
      - "Le Retour Imprévu", 1918 (Box 3)
      - "Nos Intimes", 1919 (Box 3)
      - "L'Ami Fritz", 1920 (Box 4)
      - "Le Bourgeois Gentilhomme", 1921 (Box 3)
      - "La Belle Aventure", 1922 (Box 4)
      - "Bataille des Dames", 1923 (Box 3)
      - "Le Médicin malgré lui" / "L'Anglais tel qu'on le parle", 1924 (Box 3)
      - "La Farce de Maître Pathelin" / "Les Deux Sourds", 1926 (Box 3)
      - "La Sonnette d'Alarme, 1927 (Box 4)
      - "Le Docteur Miracle", 1928 (Box 3)
      - "Miquette et sa mere", 1929 (Box 3)
      - "Le Mystère d'Adam" / "Les Précieuses Ridicules", 1930 (Box 3)
      - "La souriante Madame Beudet", 1931 (Box 3)
      - "Mon Ami Teddy", 1932 (Box 3)
      - "Le Bourgeois Gentilhomme", 1933 (Box 3)
      - "Topaze", 1934 (Box 3)
      - "Le Jeu de l'Amour et du Hasard", 1935 (Box 3)
      - "Chotard et Cie", 1936 (Box 3)
      - "La Farce du Cuvier" / "L'École des Belle-Mères" / "Un Client Sérieux", 1937 (Box 3)
      - "L'Avare", 1938 (Box 3)
      - "Ces Dames aux Chapeaux Verts", 1939 (Box 4)
      - "Les Jours Heureux", 1940 (Box 3)
      - "Le Jeu de l'Amour et du Hasard", 1941 (Box 3)
      - "Le Belle Aventure", 1942 (Box 3)
      - "La Monde où l'on s'ennuie", 1943 (Box 3)
      - "Ces Dames aux Chapeaux Verts", 1945 (Box 3)
      - "Les Femmes Savante", 1946 (Box 3)
      - "Le Malade Imaginaire", 1947 (Box 3)
      - "Les Corbeaux", 1948 (Box 3)
      - "La Belle Aventure", 1949 (Box 3)
      - "Les Jours Heureux", 1950 (Box 3)
      - "Le Jeu de l'Amour et du Hasard", 1951 (Box 3)
      - "La Monde où l'on s'ennuie", 1952 (Box 3)
      - "Le Tartuffe", 1953 (Box 3)
      - "Ces Dames aux Chapeaux Verts", 1954 (Box 4)
      - "L'Avare", 1955 (Box 4)
      - "Le Bourgeois Gentilhomme", 1956 (Box 3)
      - "La Cantatrice Chauve", Undated (Box 3)
    - Cercle Français Soirées
      - "Un Monsieur qui Prend la Mouche" (Box 3)
    - Denys Amiel, after, 1923 (Box 4)
    - E.L. Adams, 1908 (Box 3)
    - Sigma Delta Pi Membership, circa 1948-1964 (Box 3)
    - Sociedad Hispanica Play, circa 1954-1955 (Box 3)
    - Romance Languages Staff, 1907 (Box 4)
    - Alumni with Professorships
      - Laura G. Durand, French, 1963 (Box 4)
      - Glyn P. Norton, French, 1968 (Box 4)
      - Allan H. Pasco, French, 1968 (Box 4)
      - Lawrence D. Kritzman, French, 1976 (Box 4)
  - Photographic Album
    - La Maison Francaise / Casa Española, 1948 (Box 4)
  - Sound Recordings (Box 5)
    - Record, Haden, How to Pronounce Spanish, 1953 (Box 5)
    - Magnetic Tape Reels, National Defense Education Act (NDEA) Institute nos. 1-4, 1968 (Box 5)
- Publications
  The Department of Romance Languages and Literatures Publications series is divided into four subseries: Bibliographies, Brochures, Flyers, and Newsletters.
  The Brochures subseries contains paper brochures that advertise the department. The Flyers subseries contains flyers that would be mailed or posted in order to advertise Department events such as lectures.
  The Newsletters subseries is further subdivided by publication title. The Department of Romance Languages and Literatures is a 2003 newsletter most likely mailed to alumni. The Department Weekly Calendar and Announcement was a weekly newsletter containing a list of Department and University events such as speakers, Department-related announcements ranging from calls for papers to classifieds. El Bitoque and El Campanario are Spanish-language publications from 1955. Romance Language News is a periodic publication from 1989-1994 and The Weekly Tongue appears to be its predecessor from 1977-1981. Volumes 2 and 3 of the Weekly Tongue are found loose in folders and also are bound in their entirely.
  - Bibliographies
    - A Bibliography of the Members of the Department of Romance Languages of the University of Michigan (1852-1937) by Camillo P. Merlino (Box 5)
  - Brochures, undated (Box 5)
  - Flyers, 1991-1999; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Newsletters
    - Department of Romance Languages and Literatures, 2003 (Box 5)
    - Department Weekly Calendar and Announcements
      - 1987-1988 (Box 5)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 5)
      - 1989-1990 (Box 5)
      - 1990-1991 (Box 5)
      - 1991-1992 (Box 5)
    - El Bitoque, 1955 (Box 5)
    - El Campanario, 1955 (Box 5)
    - Romance Language News, 1989-1994 (Box 5)
    - The Weekly Tongue
      - Vol. 1, 1977-1978 (Box 5)
      - Vol. 2, 1978-1979 (Box 5)
      - Vol. 3, 1979-1980 (Box 5)
      - Vol. 4, 1980-1981 (Box 5)